Today, we will take a look at the
so-called “Seven circles theorem”.
While the statement of the theorem can
be expressed in simple geometric terms,
the method we will use to prove it delves into
seemingly unrelated concepts
from hyperbolic geometry.
It involves a surprising change of perspective
between Euclidean and hyperbolic space.
On the way we will learn about two
different models of hyperbolic space,
how distances are measured
as well as circles and polygons
in this hyperbolic setting.
Mind you, this is not the
only way to prove our theorem.
The first proofs of the seven circles theorem
in the 1970s did not wander through
the lands of hyperbolic geometry
but used mainly euclidean methods.
Let us now finally take a look
at the seven circles theorem.
Let C be a circle containing six smaller circles,
such that each inner circle
is tangent to the outer circle
and any two adjacent inner circles
are also tangent to each other.
Let us also draw the hexagon formed by the
intersection points of each inner circle
with the outer circle.
The Seven Circles Theorem then states that
the three main diagonals of the hexagon
will always meet at a single point.
Our goal is to now prove this statement.
We will be able to do this by embedding
the problem into a hyperbolic framework.
First, we give a small
introduction to hyperbolic geometry
to then rephrase the problem
in this setting with our newly gained knowledge.
Axiomatically, hyperbolic space
differs from Euclidean space
in that the parallel axiom does not hold.
The parallel axiom states that for every straight
line g and every point P that does not lie on g,
there is exactly one straight line h
that runs through P and is parallel to g.
By “parallel” we only mean
that they do not intersect.
This property does not hold in hyperbolic space.
Here, for every line g and point P there
are several — even infinitely many —
straight lines through P which are parallel
to g, meaning they do not intersect g.
However, our representation here is misleading.
Of course, g will be intersected
by all but the original line h
if we follow them long enough.
Generally, we have the problem that
we want to represent hyperbolic space
in the Euclidean plane, namely this video.
So the question we are addressing now is:
How can we represent the
hyperbolic in the Euclidean plane?
There are different models
for the hyperbolic plane.
Such models simply map the
hyperbolic to the Euclidean plane.
We take a closer look at the
Poincaré and Klein models.
There are however multiple other models
which can be helpful in other contexts.
First, let's take a closer
look at the Poincaré model.
The representation of the hyperbolic plane in
the Poincaré model is limited to the unit disk.
The geodesics of the Poincaré model are —
unlike straight lines in Euclidean space —
circle segments that intersect
the unit circle at a right angle.
This illustrates why the parallel
axiom does not apply here:
For a point P and a geodesic
g, we can find arbitrarily many
other geodesics that intersect P but not g.
Even if it appears that way at first glance,
the hyperbolic plane is by no means limited.
If we let a point move in one
direction with constant speed,
we notice that it never reaches
the boundary of the Poincaré model.
The unit circle itself does not belong to
the Poincaré model and can not be reached.
This distortion can be visualized by
looking at a tiling of the hyperbolic plane.
All these triangles have the
same hyperbolic shape and area.
The Poincaré model thus provides a highly
distorted representation of hyperbolic space.
Now, let us consider the Klein model.
We will see strong similarities
to the Poincaré model.
The biggest difference is that geodesics
here actually correspond to Euclidean lines.
As in the Poincaré model, we
are limited by the unit circle.
Thus, the parallel axiom
does not apply here either.
The Klein model also gives a very distorted
represenation of hyperbolic space.
Here, we see the same tiling as
before, now in the Klein model.
Distances become larger and
larger towards the border,
making the triangles seem
smaller, the closer we get to it.
Since both models represent the same space,
it is natural that there are mappings
that identify the points of
the models with each other.
We call them f and f^-1.
As we see here, the formulas for
these maps are fairly simple.
With f and f^-1, we can now transfer objects from
one model to the other, specifically geodesics.
Since the maps act pointwise, intersections
between geodesics are preserved.
This helps us rephrase the Seven Circles Theorem:
Let C be a circle containing six smaller circles,
such that each inner circle
is tangent to the outer circle
and any two adjacent inner circles
are also tangent to each other.
Drawing the hyperbolic hexagon
formed by the intersection points
of each inner circle with the outer circle,
the three main diagonals will
always meet at a single point.
After having proven this new statement,
we simply apply the transformation
from the Poincaré to the Klein model
and have thus also proven the original theorem.
Now we introduce some new
concepts in hyperbolic space.
Let's take a closer look at the behavior
of circles and their radii in this setting.
To do this, we compare it to Euclidean
circles we are familiar with.
A circle consists of all points that are
the same distance from their center P.
In Euclidean space, we measure distance
with the Euclidean distance function.
Hyperbolic disks, which we embed in the Poincaré
model, are defined exactly like Euclidean circles.
Except here, we use a different
distance function to measure lengths.
At the center of the Poincaré disk, the hyperbolic
circles look the same as the Euclidean ones.
If we now change the center,
the shape of the hyperbolic circles still
corresponds to that of the Euclidean circles,
but the center of the Euclidean circles no longer
corresponds to that of the hyperbolic ones.
Let's take a closer look at the hyperbolic radius.
It is defined using the
hyperbolic distance function,
which measures the distance between two
points b and c in the hyperbolic plane.
For the calculation, we need the
intersection points of the geodesic
with the border of the unit disk.
We call these points a and d.
To evaluate the hyperbolic distance function,
we interpret points a through d
as numbers in the complex plane.
It might not look like it,
but the hyperbolic circle has the same
distance to its center at every point.
If we move the hyperbolic center to the border
and look at the associated concentric circles,
the hyperbolic radius converges to
infinity and we get so-called horodisks.
After obtaining an intuition
for circles in hyperbolic space,
we now want to also understand
hyperbolic hexagons.
From there on, we will be able to
define the alternating perimeter,
which is of great importance to our main theorem.
A hyperbolic polygon is
defined as in Euclidean space.
However, we will represent the
curves connecting the vertices
as circle segments, as
always in the Poincaré model.
The corners of the polygon can be
anywhere in the hyperbolic plane.
If the vertices all lie on the border of the
Poincaré disk, we call our polygon ideal.
As in the Euclidean case,
the perimeter of a hyperbolic polygon can
be defined as the sum of the sidelengths.
Note that we are measuring the
hyperbolic distance between the vertices.
In the case of hexagons, an even number of corners
can be used to define an alternating perimeter.
Instead of taking the sum of all sidelengths,
we now calculate the alternating sum,
i.e., subtract every other length.
So now let's look at the alternating
perimeter of an ideal hexagon.
The problem here is that
the individual segments S_k
have infinite length since they touch the border.
Therefore, we cannot calculate the
alternating perimeter directly.
However, geodesic segments that do not
touch the boundary have finite length.
We will take advantage of this.
We define the alternating perimeter of an ideal
hexagon using that of a non-ideal hexagon.
Since its edges have finite length,
we can explicitly calculate
the alternating perimeter here.
To do this, consider a sequence P_n
of hyperbolic non-ideal hexagons
that converge to an ideal hexagon P_∞.
We now put a disk at each vertex of P_n
so that consecutive disks do not overlap.
Further we define S_k^~ as the length of
the edge between the borders of the disks.
Obviously, these S_k^~ are finite.
If we change the radius of
a disk, we add and subtract
the same amount from the alternating perimeter.
In this case S_1^~ and S_6^~ are changed.
Therefore, the alternating perimeter is
independent of the size of our disks,
in particular when our disks have radius zero.
Thus, the alternating sum of S_k is
equal to the alternating sum of S_k^~.
If we let n go towards infinity,
this equality still holds.
But since the lengths S_k^~ are now finite,
we have actually found a meaningful
calculation for the alternating perimeter.
Now let's consider an ideal hexagon.
If we connect the opposite sides of this
hexagon, a triangle appears in the middle.
Let's call this triangle T_P.
We now prove the following equality:
For any ideal hexagon, the absolute
value of the alternating perimeter
is exactly twice the perimeter of T_P.
For the proof we first define the
notion of a semi-ideal triangle.
It has two corners on the
boundary of the circle, i.e., ideal points,
and one corner
in the hyperbolic plane.
In our ideal hexagon, there are three
such triangles: Y_1, Y_2 and Y_3.
Three other semi-ideal triangles
which intersect the inner triangle T_P
can be found opposite to the Y_k triangles.
We call them G_1, G_2 and G_3.
For hyperbolic triangles, we define a notion
similar to the alternating perimeter.
If we add disjoint horodisks at the
two ideal vertices of the triangle,
we get lengths L_1', L_2' and L_3'.
We use this to define the alternating perimeter
of a semi-ideal triangle by adding the two
blue lengths and subtracting the red one.
The alternating perimeter does not
depend on the size of each circle,
since the same length is
both added and subtracted.
The triangles G_k and Y_k each share
exactly one vertex for k = 1, 2 and 3.
In each case, there is an isometry I_k that
maps opposite triangles onto each other.
We can construct these isometries as follows:
With the help of so-called Möbius transformations
— isometries in the hyperbolic plane —
we can map the intersection of
the two triangles to the origin.
The two diagonals that intersect the point are
now both straight lines through the origin.
Therefore, we can simply perform
a point reflection at the origin,
transforming one triangle onto the other.
Of course, the whole thing works not
only for the first pair of triangles,
but for all three of them.
Since we have an isometry
between the two triangles,
their alternating perimeter is the same.
We can write these formulas explicitly for all
three pairs of triangles and bring the perimeter
of G_k to the other
side.
By adding everything together,
we obtain the following formula.
But what does this sum actually represent?
Let's look at the sum in the picture.
If we subtract the alternating
perimeter of the G_i,
a part of the sum cancels out with
the alternating perimeter of the Y_i.
We notice that we obtain twice the
perimeter of the inner triangle
as well as the alternating
perimeter of the hexagon.
Overall, our equality follows.
Now we are finally ready to
prove the Seven Circles Theorem.
Let's look at an ideal hyperbolic hexagon
with circles tangent to the large circle
such that adjacent circles
touch at a single point.
Taking a look at the alternating
perimeter of this hexagon,
we notice that the hexagon
segments in the circles cancel out.
Therefore, the alternating perimeter is zero.
So the perimeter of the triangle in the middle
is also zero, using the equality we just proved.
Thus, the main diagonals of the
hexagon must meet at a single point.
All that's left is to perform the transformation
from the Poincaré model back to the Klein model.
As mentioned before, the diagonals
continue to run through a single point.
This corresponds exactly to the scenario
from the original Seven Circles Theorem
which we have thus proved.